Hey, Brett Contrarus here. Um, this
video is going to go over um different
types of rotational um core exercises um
specifically different types of chops
and lifts and uh paloff presses. But, um
this is something that I think a lot of
people just kind of gloss over. They see
it and they just don't think it's that
effective. But once you do it, when I
make people try it, trainers, coaches,
they're always amazed at how effective
it is. And one reason why I like these
so much is you really get a lot of power
in it. But it doesn't just work the core
muscles as far as, you know, pelvis to
rib cage muscles. It also works the the
hips, you know, the glutes, glute
medius, upper glute max. Um, and uh, you
know, you can you can I'm going to show
you how to tinker with different
variables to to, you know, make the the
exercise more challenging um, for
certain reasons. So, the first uh, thing
I'm going to show you um is a cable
lift. Um, so there's a lot of different
ways you can do things. You can do
things standing in um, you know, kind of
an athletic stance here. Um, this would
be called a parallel stance. You can do
things in a staggered stance. So either
way, um you can do things from your
knees. This would be called tall
kneeling. And you can do these um from a
half kneeling position like this. I
think my favorite would be half
kneeling. Um I want to say um give
credit real quick. I learned these from
Great Cook and he has a special bar that
he made. It's called the cook bar. I'll
be using a rope when I do this today,
but I have a cook bar back home and I
freaking love it. I think it's one of
the most amazing pieces of equipment for
for rotational training. There's it's
unbeatable. So, the cook bar is super
long. It attaches to to the cable and
you get a lot of torque in there because
of how long it is. Um anyway, you can
still use a rope and here I have um this
is like an Eric's pad here, so it really
helps to have something to kneel on.
Okay. So, first thing I'm going to show
you is a a cable lift, half kneeling.
But see, if I take a wide stance like
this, I kind of get spread out. Now, I
can go heavier because my my base of
support is widened. So, from here, I can
really go
heavy. You know, I can crank this up.
So, I always there's never any slack in
the rope. I bring it like this and then
press it. Okay. Now, I'll show you with
a narrower stance. Um, and I'm going to
get my base of support lined up. So, now
it becomes more challenging for the
hips. This is hard to balance. Okay. So,
So, just two different ways to do things
with a wide base of support and a narrow
base of support. As you can see, this
for a lot of beginner clients, this here
is just challenging staying in this
position here. And then you add stuff to
it, it makes it even harder. So, um,
again, the lift is starting low and
coming high. The chop is opposite. So,
um here's a a half kneeling version.
Okay. From here to
there. And then, um you can do it
standing, staggered.
Okay. Um and also I can change the
angle, the orientation of my body. So,
if I want I can now go more straight out
like this.
So, it's different when you're going
facing having the direction of the
vector load vector coming this way
compared to coming this way. So, here's
all these different ways to toy around
with it that I'm showing you. Okay. Now,
I'm going to move it
up to here. All right. Same different. I
can do all the same things. So half
kneeling wide
base. Okay, this one I can go a little
bit
heavier. So right there, I'm feeling my
glute big time. The the rear glute is
working overtime here and also through
the core. Um, all right. So notice when
I do these, my outside leg is uh is
forward and my inside leg this changes
when I go to chops. Okay. So trying to
think of some different things. I can do
it more orientated from this
direction. Okay. Awesome
exercise. All right. And now I'm going
to show you. how obviously you would do
both sides. If I did three, you know,
five reps on this leg, I would switch
and do the other leg, too. And then now
I'm going to show you chops. Okay,
chops. I'm going to do the other way.
I'm going to have the inside leg forward
and the outside leg backwards. So, this
one, um, go a little bit lighter
here. This one
Okay, half
kneeling. And uh you know I can change
the angle and more this way if I
want. So you can toy around with all
these different variables. There's no
kind of right and wrong way. Um, you
know, as long as you're just feeling it,
working the right muscles. You can go
low, you can go medium, you can go high,
you can do wide base to support, narrow
base. again parallel stance, tall
kneeling stance, staggered stance, half
kneeling stance. And then you can do
kind of facing
um I guess this would be called like a
you know I guess you'd say parallel with
the cable stack or you could do it
facing away from it, facing
perpendicular to it. So there's a lot of
different variables and now I'll go over
the peloff press real quick. Um, this is
another awesome exercise here. And I'm
going to show you a wide stance and a
narrow stance. So, here's the peloff
press. I can go from here. Um, I'm going
to show you here. I'm going to have a
narrow stance and just go straight out.
Hold it. Come back
in. Okay.
Now, I can also go super heavy on this.
Okay. That's like 66 kg. about, you
know, that's like 150 lbs. I can get a
really wide base of support. Okay, come
here. And now I just kind
of Okay, so you can see that's really
tough. Get a wide base. You can go super
heavy on it. And then the last one I
want to show you is
um you can do a paloff press to
overhead. Come back down.
So, lots of different great rotary
exercises. I really like these ones
because they work your core um you know,
abdominal and erector muscles and at the
same time they work your hip and glute
muscles. So, hope you enjoy the video.
Thanks a lot for watching.